<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a gentleman in the city to a gentleman in the country about the odiousness of persecution, occasioned by the late rigorous proceedings against sober dissenters, by certain angry justices in the country</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B25835</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827799</idno>
  <idno type="VID">206886</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264214679</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1388</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827799</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99827799e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B25835)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206886)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1853:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a gentleman in the city to a gentleman in the country about the odiousness of persecution, occasioned by the late rigorous proceedings against sober dissenters, by certain angry justices in the country</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Relgious tolerance --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206886:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206886:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM A GENTLEMAN in the CITY TO A GENTLEMAN in the COUNTRY, ABOUT THE Odiousness of Persecution, Occasioned by the late Rigorous Proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Sober Dissenters, by certain Angry Justices in the COUNTRY</p>
            <q>It is the part of the <hi>Christian</hi>-Religion to Suffer, and not to make People Suffer for Religion, <bibl>
                  <hi>Tertul. Apol.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1677.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:206886:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:206886:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE News of a Persecution meerly for a matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, at this time a day, when the whole Nation ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears professedly to dislike it; and the giving counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to Informers (who are the Pest of every Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the common Enemies of Property) to the Prejudice of peaceable People, and those owned to be <hi>Protestants,</hi> and known to have had no hand in the late National Quarrels, makes your Friends, who have had notice of your late Troubles, suspect that there is something in your case more then ordinary.</p>
            <p>Had this fallen out in some remote Country, where no Informer had ever yet appeared, we might have conceived, that through Ignorance that sort of Devil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> might have been mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for an Angel of Light; and that upon his bare averment, some well-meaning Persons, even against their own Experience, might have been induced to mistake their peaceable Neighbours for Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Incendiaries, and unworthy to enjoy their own proper Goods. Or had this happened in a place more near, where the Name of an Informer had been heard, and his Malignity under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood in the general; but where, through want of conversing with <hi>Westminsterhall</hi> and <hi>Guildhall,</hi> they might have taken the Fiend to have had more power, and more skill in fencing then in truth he hath; it would not have been esteemed a very strange thing, that a Magistrate should have been found out, who ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it to be an impossible thing to secure himself against the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil without some sacrifice, should rather choose to make an Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him of his Neighbours Goods, then to run the hazard of losing his own. But to hear of a Persecution for Religion in a Country which lies so near <hi>France,</hi> where <hi>Protestants</hi> are allowed their publick Temples, under a Government zealously <hi>Popish:</hi> To see an Informer, the Spie and Scout against property, encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the great Country of property, and that for peaceable
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:206886:3"/> Conscience; and in a Country of so much good Nature and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spitallity. But to see that sort of Creature concerned in a County so neer <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westmin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er,</hi> as not to be capable of not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what Informers are, how detestable their Trade, how inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable their Power, how generally indigent and dissolute, how mean their Skill, how little they know more then to subborn Witnesses to commit Perjuries, which are discovered to their Confusion, is that which raiseth Wonder in some of your Friends to so great an height, that they generally request from your own hand the true state of your Cas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in all its Circumstances, to the end they may know, whether there be any thing which can differ it from the common Cases of Persecution meerly for Religion; from which the generality of the Country Gentlemen of <hi>England</hi> (and particularly those of the Country where you live) do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly profess to have as great an abhorrency, as they have from Depopulating of Countries, which is the Effect that such Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions must of necessity produce. In the mean time, do not (I pray take me to be one, who think it strange to hear of Troubles; what hath been formerly may happen again without Astonishment; &amp; you are too well known to be thought to be surprized or afraid.</p>
            <p>Well did that Person consider the Creature <hi>Man,</hi> who distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished him into two parts, viz. <hi>the Man,</hi> and <hi>the Beast:</hi> But it were happy for Mankind, if the <hi>Beast</hi> were less imperious and cruel: In truth it is hard to find where <hi>the Man</hi> is allowed to have any power in Acting; every thing seems so totally and absolutely to be governed by <hi>the Beast,</hi> and by the Tyranny of its inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Passions and Senses.</p>
            <p>Where shall one find yet a single Person in the World, who calls himself a <hi>Christian,</hi> or that Party of Men who desire to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed <hi>Christians,</hi> but he and they will readily grant that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, Mat. 7.12. <hi>All things whatsoever ye would that men should do to you, do you even so to them; for this is the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets:</hi> and that other Principle, Rom. 3.8. <hi>Let us not do Evil that Good may come,</hi> to be Gospel-Principles, and oblieging to all Mankind.</p>
            <p>There is not a Politition or States-Man, nor a Government any where, that owns <hi>Christianity</hi> to be the true Religion, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:206886:3"/> That in the Council of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which was assembled in order to the Persecuting of the Apostles for Matters of meer Religion, <hi>Gamaliel</hi> advised prudently, and according to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of true Religion, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. <hi>Let them alone, for if this counsel, or this work be of men, it will come to nought; but if it be of God, we cannot overthrow it, least happily we be found even to sight against God:</hi> They will all confess readily, when pressed with these cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable and peaceable Principles; that the Spirit of persecuting for meer Religion, is a Spirit of Injustice, as not doing to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as our selves would be done unto; and a Spirit of disfiance and incredulity, refusing to trust God, and his providence, with the defence and justification of what is professed to be of God: and yet it is hard to find that single Person, and much more to Name, that Community or Government amongst <hi>Christians,</hi> now in being, whose practise, when they have opertunity, and power, are not contrary to their Principles: And not only so, but they will take upon them to justifie such practises to be consistant with, nay, even duties unto which they are obliged by that pure Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they take upon them to prosess to the whole World.</p>
            <p>But to the end I may not be esteemed presumptuous, or uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable in what I here assert, and in regard it is impossible to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce evident proofs for what I say, as touching single persons, let us a little examine the matter, as to Parties and Governments, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this for granted, that every particular party calls it self a true Church, or the true Church of Christ: If what is here urged of differing Churches shall be proved true, the presumption will stand very strong as to single persons; there being no single person, who would be esteemed a <hi>Christian,</hi> but he is in communion or fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with some Church, which he owns to be the true Church of Christ, and by whose Judgment he is willing to be concluded, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a professed Member of it, and as taking it for his Principle; that every Member of the true Church of Christ ought to be of her Judgment, because the Scripture sayes, <hi>She is the Pillar and Ground of Truth;</hi> and though some boggle at this, yet nothing is truer then that every <hi>Christian</hi> Society daily practiseth it.</p>
            <p>Now, the better to prepare the way for this intended Tryal, we will crave the Liberty first, to consider <hi>Christianity</hi> in the World
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:206886:4"/> in general, in its first Ages, when it was under Persecution for meer matter of Religion, and before it gained any civil Power and Dominion, from them we shall know what the true <hi>Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> did teach; we will then consider <hi>Christianity</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> when divided only into two distinct Parties, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Protestants</hi> and the <hi>Papists;</hi> and in the last place, we will consider <hi>Christianity</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> when the <hi>Protestants</hi> were subdivided into several Parties, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Episcopal,</hi> or Church of <hi>England Protestants,</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> the <hi>Independents,</hi> the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> and the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers:</hi> and when the <hi>Papists</hi> were become fo small, that they were upon the matter inconsiderable, and I suppose from these differing times, we may hope for a reasonable Information.</p>
            <p>First, Then suppose the question put to the <hi>Christians</hi> of the first and Primitive Times, under those first and greatest Persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, under which Christianity then suffered. <hi>Is it lawful to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute, and to make and execute Laws for the Inflicting of Pains and Penalties upon quiet and peaceable People for matters, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Religion;</hi> and in particular, <hi>for meeting together meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for matter of Religion?</hi> Doubtless, their answer would have been given with one general Voice: <hi>That it was not lawful;</hi> and that it was against the rule of Christ, and the Law of Nature, <hi>Quod Tibi non vis Alteri no feceris, Do not unto another, what thou wouldst not have done unto thy self.</hi> And that True it is, the <hi>Jews,</hi> who persecuted the Lord of Life, and put him to Death for matter of meer Religion, did alledge for their Justification, that <hi>they had a Law,</hi> and that <hi>by their Law he ought to die:</hi> But that, that Law, and all Laws of that Nature, were against the Law of God; and that the <hi>Christians</hi> had <hi>no such custom, nor the Churches of Christ,</hi> is, I think, a most undenyable thing.</p>
            <p>These Ages (by the agreement of all) were esteemed the purest Ages of Christianity; Religion being then most pure, when the Professors of it weremost poor. And if any one shall conceive, that the <hi>Christians</hi> of those Ages, would have given any other answer, contrary to what I have here framed for them, and shall give a convincing Reason for such his appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension, I shall confess my mistake. In the mean time I must say, that I cannot see what other answer they could have given,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:206886:4"/> but what must have justified the Persecutions against themselves to have been innocent, on the part of the Persecutors, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved those first <hi>Christians</hi> to Err in Religion, and to be disturbers of the Peace, and Government of their Countries; and their Meetings to be unlawful Assemblies: And much more Innocent on the part of the inferiour Magistrates, who took care to put those Laws in Execution; they being as much obliged in all civil Respects, to put in Execution the Laws of their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, as our Inferiour Magistrates are obliged to the Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Laws; and they gave the same Reasons: And the same is to be said in the Case of the Persecution of our Lord Christ, as seems very clear from that Prayer, which he offered for his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors: <hi>Father, forgive them, they know not what they do;</hi> here then is a Principle of Christianity undivided.</p>
            <p>In the next place, we are to consider Christianity in <hi>England,</hi> when divided only into two distinct Parties, <hi>viz. Protestants</hi> and <hi>Papists,</hi> and when the <hi>Protestants</hi> had made no Subdivision amongst themselves here. This I take to be in the times of K. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. K. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> and part of the Reign of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> for though there were diversities of Opinions amongst <hi>Protestants,</hi> as well here as in other Countries, even in their first beginnings; yet they were not divided into parties, being every where upon the Defensive. In the time of K. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. which I intend to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance in, both parties were Persecuted.</p>
            <p>The Case stands thus, that King at his coming to the Crown, found the whole Nation in a quiet possession of Popery, &amp; holding it as an Article of their Faith, and the Principle whereon they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the unity of their Faith depended, that <hi>The Pope was the Supream Pastor and visible Head of Government next under Christ, of that which they then called the Catholick Church of Christ, of which the then National Church of</hi> England <hi>was a Member:</hi> The King had defended this Article by Writing so vigorously, that the Pope had for that very work conferred upon him the Title of <hi>Defender of the Faith,</hi> to be enjoyed and used by him, and his Successors forever. The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> after this threw off this Supream Pastour, this visible Head, and put this King into his place; so far as concerned the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:206886:5"/> the Title of <hi>Supream Head of the Church of England,</hi> annexed to the Crown; and this by a Law, 26 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. C. 1. And then by another Law, 26 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. C. 13. It was Enacted, <hi>That if any by Word or Writing, should attempt to deprive the King of the Title of his Royal Estate, he should be adjudged a Traytor:</hi> This change of the Headship of the Church, was, and is truly (at least in <hi>England</hi>) a <hi>Protestant</hi> Doctrine; and undoubtedly there is no <hi>Protestant</hi> whatsoever, but approves the casting off the Popes Headship, as conformable with the Doctrine of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants.</hi> And upon the latter of these two Laws, divers suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed death for their denying the Kings Supremacy; this was the first step made in <hi>England,</hi> from Popery towards Protestancy. And the Vigorous Execution of this latter Law, encouraged several <hi>Protestants</hi> from forraign parts to come into <hi>England,</hi> not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but to have a Liberty to exercise their Religion here; and it gave confidence to many of the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> to receive, and to others, to entertain good thoughts of <hi>Protestancy;</hi> being perswaded, that after the sheding of so much Blood, as had been shed here upon that Occasion, <hi>England</hi> would never any more admit of the Article of the Popes Supremacy; and Consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, would every day make greater steps from that Church, of which the Pope was owned to be the Supream Pastour. And certain it is, that <hi>Protestancy</hi> upon this Occasion also made its entrance into <hi>England,</hi> and gained Ground here, and such (if not by open application to the King for that purpose yet) at least in their Hearts desired a Toleration, and to be admitted to Preach, and Exercise their Religion here, without being Persecuted for their so doing; so that their Principle was at that time (at least) against Persecution for meer Religion. But <hi>Protestancy</hi> being now taken notice of to grow, another Law was made, 31 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. for set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tling unity of Opinion in the six Articles therein named, by which the denyal of Tansubstantiation, and several other Doctrines therein named, are Enacted to be punished with Death.</p>
            <p>And now Persecution in <hi>England,</hi> for matters of meer Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion grew sharp and high; so that it is observed by our Histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that upon one &amp; the same day, some who were professed <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,</hi> were put to death for denying the Kings Supremacy,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:206886:5"/> which was a <hi>Protestant</hi> Article; and some who were professed <hi>Protestants,</hi> were put to death for denying Transubstantiation, which was an Article of the <hi>Papists;</hi> so that at this time, the Government could neither be said to be <hi>Popish,</hi> nor <hi>Protestant,</hi> but both parties were persecuted most severely for matters of meer Religion: and he who should then have said to either party, in justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Proceedings of the Magistrate in the Execution of either of those Laws, that that party did not then suffer for any matter of meer Religion, but for breaking of the Peace, in breaking of the Kings Laws, would certainly have been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken not to have understood those Laws, or the cause of their then Suffering. And now, suppose each of these parties seperately interrogated, when thus under Persecution (for <hi>Afflictio dat Intellectum</hi>) Is it lawful to Persecute, and to make and Execute Laws, for the Inflicting of Pains &amp; Penalties upon quiet &amp; peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able People, for matters of <hi>meer Religion?</hi> most certainly each party in their then present Circumstances, would have answered in the Negative; that it was not lawful: They would not have fallen into the debate to consider what Religion their Persecutors were of, whether of the <hi>Popish</hi> or <hi>Protestant,</hi> to the end, to have fixt the Cruelty and Injustice of persecuting for a matter of meer Religion, upon that party, as a Principle of that Religion, which their Fancies should have perswaded them to have been the Religion of their Persecutors; the <hi>Papists</hi> would not have then stood formalizing that, because the first Persecution was occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned upon the denyal of the Kings Headship over the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which was a <hi>Protestant</hi> Doctrine, in opposition to the Popes Headship, which was the <hi>Popish</hi> Doctrine; therefore the <hi>Protestants</hi> were the Agressors in the Persecution; and therefore the Principle of Persecution was a <hi>Protestant</hi> Principle; And therefore, the Persecution of the <hi>Protestants</hi> afterwards was no other then a just Judgment of God drawn upon the <hi>Protestants</hi> by themselves, as a Consequence of that Principle of Persecution, which gave them the first occasion or oppertunity of introducing their Religion into <hi>England;</hi> nor would the <hi>Protestants</hi> by way of Recrimination have charged the <hi>Papists</hi> then, that because that King and the then Government were of the <hi>Popish</hi> Religion in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:206886:6"/> every point, save only in the Article touching the Supremacy; therefore the Principle of Persecution must necessarily be a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish</hi> Principle: No, they would most certainly each party have disclaimed the Principle, as unwarranted by the Principles of true <hi>Christianity,</hi> which each of them claimed to be theirs, and each of them would have agreed, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it was their common Principle to do unto others as they desired ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers should do unto them; here we see the Principle of <hi>Christianity</hi> in <hi>England</hi> when di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided.</p>
            <p>The Persecutions before mentioned, being quieted by the Death of K. <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, and the Crown descending unto K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, an Infant of such tender Years, as made him uncapable of Exercising the Government in his own Person, not being com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the use of right Reason; the Duke of <hi>Somerset</hi> took upon him the Administraction of all things, under the Title of <hi>Protector,</hi> and with him the <hi>Protestant</hi> party had their sole Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest. Several Penal Laws were made in this Kings Reign, for the Inflicting Pains and Penalties for matters of meer Religion, which gave occasion to the <hi>Papists</hi> to charge upon <hi>Protestants</hi> the Principle of Persecution for matters of meer Religion as their Principle: It is true, the <hi>Papists</hi> were at that time Sufferers, and were actually Persecuted by the then Government for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of meer Religion; but true Charity might easily have found other Reasons, unto which those Persecutions might warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly have been Asigned, and there was certainly no necessity of Assigning them to any Principle of the <hi>Protestants;</hi> the first Law which was made, relating to these matters, was 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. C. 1. touching the Lords Supper, Entituled, <hi>The Penalties for speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing against the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Christ, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the receiving thereof in both kinds:</hi> This seems to have no other tendency then barely to keep both Parties from falling to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by the Ears, and the <hi>Protestants</hi> were more likely to fall under the Punishment of this Law then the <hi>Papists:</hi> none could say that it was the effect of Intemperate Spirits; for though it directed Communion in both kinds, to such as desired to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate; yet it compelled not any person to communicate: And it had a Clause of great Temperance in the very close of it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:206886:6"/> in these words, <hi>Not condemning hereby the usuage of any Church out of the Kings Majesties Dominions.</hi> The next Law of this Nature, was made in the same Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 <hi>Edward</hi> 6. C. 12. It is Entituled thus, <hi>viz. Statutes concerning Treasons, &amp;c. repealed;</hi> and this cannot be denyed to be sharp against the <hi>Papists.</hi> It makes it highly Penal to affirm, <hi>That the King is not, or ought not to be Supream Head on Earth of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>or any of them immediately under God; or that the Bishop of</hi> Rome, <hi>or any other Person or Persons, other then the King of</hi> England <hi>for the time being, is, or ought to be by the Laws of God Supream Head of the same Churches, or any of them:</hi> But there is no necessity or reason of ass ribing this to any <hi>Protestant</hi> Principle, though it is supposed to be made in affirmance of a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant</hi> Principle. Another penal Law was made 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. Entituled, <hi>The Penalty for not using Ʋniformity of Service and Administration of Sacraments.</hi> And in 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. C. 10. was made an Act, <hi>For the abolishing and putting away of divers Books and Images:</hi> Both which were severe against the <hi>Papists</hi> in matters of meer Religion; yet do I not find any necessity why the Persecutions, which these Statutes occasioned, should be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to any <hi>Protestant</hi> Principle. During the whole Reign of this Infant King, it is clear, that the <hi>Papists</hi> suffered Persecution from the Hands of the <hi>Protestants</hi> for matters of meer Religion; and without doubt, had it been then demanded of the <hi>Papists,</hi> whether such Persecutions and such Laws Enacting such Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were lawful, and agreeable with the Principles of true <hi>Christianity,</hi> which they pretended to maintain; their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer would have been in the Negative: And they would then with one accord have readily agreed, that Persecution for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of meer Religion, was no more consistant with the Rule of Christ, requiring us, <hi>To do unto others, as we would that others should do unto us,</hi> then Murder and Robbery.</p>
            <p>But the Persecutions Inflicted upon the <hi>Papists,</hi> by the Law made in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, did not last long, they ended with his Life; and by the descending of the Crown to Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> the <hi>Papists</hi> were rescued from all their Sufferings. All the Laws made against them in the times of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and <hi>Edw.</hi> the 6. were Reprealed; but the case was altered with the poor
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:206886:7"/>
               <hi>Protestants,</hi> whose Sufferings were so great, and are so sharply &amp; justly reflected on, even to this day, that I, who love not to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate any thing, especially that carries its own aggravation with it, will say no more of them, but beg of our good God to blot them out of our remembrance. Sure I am, had any <hi>Protestant</hi> been asked his Judgment in that Age, touching the Principle of Persecuting for matters of meer Religion, he would have disclaimed it, as absolutely contrary to the Principles of his Religion, which is the point that I am labouring to Evince. And after all this, shall any one take it ill, if upon a Principle of Charity I shall profess, that I could never as yet see any thing offered, which in my poor apprehension did necessarily Evince; <hi>That Persecution for meer Religion, was even an avowed Principle of either side.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The bloody Fury of Persecution, under which the <hi>Protestants</hi> suffered so miserably in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> time, did end with her Reign, which was but short; and after that, the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> never suffered more from the <hi>Papists.</hi> But upon the death of Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> the Crown coming to Q. <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and she thereupon declaring her self a firm, a zealous, and to all intents, religiously a <hi>Potestant,</hi> the edge came strong against the <hi>Papists,</hi> before any differences were discerned to be among the <hi>Protestants.</hi> Several of the Popish Clergy suffered Persecution some even unto Death in several parts of the Kingdom: And new Laws were from time to time, framed and multiplyed for those purposes. And if now we ask the Opinion of the <hi>Papists</hi> as to Penal Laws, either Sanguinary or others, and Persecution, for meer matter of Religion; they will tell you (and they continue in that protestation even unto this day) <hi>That all such Laws and Persecutions are unlawful, and against the Principles of the Gospel:</hi> And though the <hi>Protestants</hi> under several changes, have been in the possession of those Laws, and have at times more or less Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them; yet (so far as I can find) they do not own Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution for matters meerly of Religion to be their Principle, or lawful.</p>
            <p>After the <hi>Papists</hi> had some time continued the alone Persecuted Party for Matters meerly of Religion, several Differences, in Matters meerly of Religion, happened to divide the <hi>Protestants</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:206886:7"/> into distinct and separate Parties during some part of the Reign of <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> and also during the several and successive Reigns of <hi>King James</hi> and <hi>King Charles</hi> the first; and about the beginning of the Reign of <hi>King James,</hi> some particular despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Malecontents, professedly of the Popish Religion, being found guilty of a most hellish Plot, whereby they had designed the Destruction both of that King and of his Parliament by Gun-powder (for which they were deservedly Executed) seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral new and more severe Laws were then, and at several times af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, made against the <hi>Papists</hi> in general, by which several Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were inflicted on them for Matters of meer Religion; and several penal Laws were also made, by which the then Governing <hi>Protestant</hi> Party, then, and still distinguished by the Name of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> or the <hi>Episcopal Party</hi> persecuted them.</p>
            <p>The Dissenting <hi>Protestants</hi> of all sorts were prosecuted under the general Name of <hi>Non-conformists,</hi> who cryed aloud to have a Toleration granted, that is, to themselves; &amp; declared it absolutely Unlawful to punish any for Matters of meer Religion; and when this (by them so much desired Toleration) could not be obtained otherwise, they took up Arms, and we all know what followed.</p>
            <p>During the continuance of this before-mentioned War, and after <hi>King Charles</hi> the first was not able to make head against the <hi>Non-conformists,</hi> the <hi>Non-conformistt</hi> retaliated the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and not a little crusht the Popish Party, both having engaged on t'other side, and being of other Religions, esteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themselves persecuted for matter of Religion.</p>
            <p>That War being ended with the Death of <hi>King Charles</hi> the first, and the expelling of our present King out of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the total Ruin of <hi>Episcopacy,</hi> and the Supression of the <hi>Papists,</hi> and the total change of the Government, the <hi>Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists</hi> under the several Forms took upon them and kept the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, until our present King was by the Divine Hand of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence restored to his Crown; during all which time the <hi>Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal</hi> Party and the <hi>Papists</hi> suffered, more or less, for matters (at least in their apprehension) meerly of Religion. But these two Parties were not alone in their sufferings, for during those bloody contests there appeared another party which from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:206886:8"/> its very first appearing in this Kingdom hath been severely Persecuted, and that only for matters of Religion, this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was the people called Quakers; they did at their first shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themselves in the World, go under the name of the <hi>Children of Light,</hi> because they assert as their main and first Principle, that every man and woman is inlightned with a saving Light from God, which all ought to obey on pain of Damnation; but by one <hi>Bennit</hi> a Justi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, in 1650. were nick-named <hi>Quakers,</hi> they professed themselves to adhere to the plain Principles of the first <hi>Christians,</hi> and particularly to hold it as their Principle, <hi>that all Persecution whatsoever, against any Party, People, or Person whatsoever, for matters meerly of Religion is absolutely Ʋnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Ʋnrighteous, and against the Spirit and Will of God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive of the true Christianity;</hi> and to give them their due, they have been true Contenders for their Principle, both by their frequent Apologies and Remonstrances on the one hand, and invincible patience in Suffering on the other hand.</p>
            <p>Upon the Restauration of our present King, the <hi>Episcopal</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was also restored. The <hi>Presbyterians, Independents</hi> and <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists</hi> expected a general toleration in matters of Religion ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to some of the Kings gracious Letters, as a Reward for their not opposing the Restauration of the King: The Papists also expected the same thing, as a reward for their Loyalty in adhering to the Crown; the <hi>Quakers,</hi> now a great People, grew confident of the like freedom, because of their Innofensiveness to Government. But instead of this expected liberty; all the former Penal Laws made in the respective times of Q. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> K. <hi>James.</hi> and K. <hi>Charles</hi> the first were revived and ordered to be put in Execution as well against all <hi>Non-conformists,</hi> who were <hi>Protestants,</hi> as against the <hi>Papists.</hi> And new and more severe Laws were made against them all: And by these respective pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices we see what all these parties have done when they had Power.</p>
            <p>I think such as understand the Transactions of our Country will clear me from having made any mistake as to matters of fact, in any thing that I have here said, touching past Persecutions, though I believe there will not want some who will either think me mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:206886:8"/> in the point of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arity, when I profess to believe that I do not think there is any one party now in <hi>England</hi> who holds it as a Principle of their Religion, <hi>that it is Lawfull to persecute,</hi> or to make or Execute Laws for the inflicting of Paines or Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties for any matters of meer Religion, or else they will su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect I do not in Truth bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eve what I here profess to believe in this point, since even by my own shewing in the several matters of fact before Urged by my self, it plainly appears, that there is not one party now in <hi>England</hi> (the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> only excepted) who profess themselves <hi>Christians;</hi> but have been notoriously guilty (more or less) of the very Fact, or (at least) of a publick allowing, if not abetting of it: And every party will be apt to sensure me of Singularity (at least) since each party thinks that they have Arguments drawn from Facts, sufficient to fix this ugly Doctrine as a Principle upon that Religion which they hate most. O that <hi>the Man</hi> could prevail against <hi>the Beast!</hi> and that we would permit our Passions to give way to our Reason, to consider things nakedly, and as they truly are, <hi>Si Satis est accusasse Quis erit Innocens?</hi> If to accuse be a sufficient Conviction, what party shall be able to clear it self, and who knows not that 'tis a <hi>Christians</hi> part to suffer, but never to Persecute.</p>
            <p>I very well know, that the <hi>Protestants</hi> in general, who look upon the <hi>Papists</hi> as their common Enemies, do in their Pulpits, in their Writings, and in all their Addresses to the People, charge them with those Rivers of Blood which streamed in the times of Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> and with the bloody Intentions which those miscreants had in their Hearts, who were engaged in the hellish Powder-plot; that the first was done by authority, and chiefly by the <hi>Popish</hi> Bishops, that the other, though the Fact; but of private persons, were never condemned by authority; and silence is an implyed consent and approbation. Do we well consider what the <hi>Papists</hi> offer by way of extenuation in answer to these Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages? they iustifie none of these Facts: But as to the first, they recommend to us to be considered, the Circumstances that Q. <hi>Mary</hi> was in when she came to the Crown, all the chief Heads of the <hi>Protestant</hi> party, had set up and Proclaimed the Lady <hi>Jane</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:206886:9"/> duly Queen, in opposition to Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> their lawful Soveraign; they had raised an Army against her; she was compelled to gain her Right by force; she was a Conquerer: And if we will believe them, she had not given any Articles which might have obliged her to pardon any who were guilty of this Usurpation, and Treason; she was told it was a Confederacy of the whole par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Protestants,</hi> which gave her a ground to suspect, that the <hi>Protestants</hi> held it for a Principle, that it was lawful for them to take up Arms aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nst, and depose their lawful Soveraign, if of a Religion contrary to them. She might by the Laws then in being (the same which we have to this day in force amongst us) have taken away the Lives of all who were any wayes Guilty of endeavouring to depose her; she did not make any one new per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecuting Law (which is considerable) by which any of those were taken off who were put to Death: But being put into fears by her Council; that without making great Examples of Justice in all parts of the Kindom, she would be in danger of having new Insurrections made by the <hi>Protestants</hi> against her, she was perswaded that the only way to prevent the sheding of more Blood for the future, was to punish considerable numbers of those who had then actually broken the old Laws of her Kingdom. Her Bishops (and that is the chief and just ground of the charge) had their fears and revenge also, in particular, they were new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly restord to their Bishopricks, and Religion, of which they had been dispossessed in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, they were afraid of being again disturbed; and these fears and pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions made them take wrong measures. They perswaded the Queen, that she might as well make Examples of Justice, and prevent future Insurrections, by punishing those for their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, who had been Guilty of Treason, as if she had punished them for Treason: and they urged, that by this way she should do her self the greater right, and give a proof to the World, that she was more offended with Treason committed against Heaven, (for so they esteemed <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion) then with Treason committed against her self, which might be interpreted Revenge; they had forgotten the true Principles of the true <hi>Christian</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which required to leave unto God to Revenge whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:206886:9"/> Injuries are done to him, and to leave it to God to judge what Injuries were done to him, <hi>They did not now think of doing unto others as they would that others should do unto them;</hi> they did not remember the wise advice of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> before mentioned, but giving Ear only to their own Fears, and preferring Human policies before Gospel-Rules, they misled the Queen, and took away the Lives of vast numbers of such against whom nothing could be c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arged, but what was matter of meer Religion, thereby giving a Just occasion to charge upon their own Religion the Principle of Persecution for meer Religion, which those who now profess that Religion, do pretend to disown and abominate. And as to the business of the Powder-plot, they pray us to observe, that it was the Treason, not of the <hi>Papists</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but of a few particular persons of Dseperate fortunes and worse Consciences, and not without suspition of being drawn into the Snare by their Enemies, that upon the most severe Scrutiny which could be made into that business, it clearly appeared, that the number of the offenders was not greater then what happens sometimes to be engaged in a particular Burglary, and not so many as to make up the fourth part of a foot Company of Souldiers, that the Villany of that design hath been as fully and generally, yea, and as publickly decryed, condemned and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated by the whole party of the <hi>English Papists</hi> of that Age, and of all succeeding Ages, as any thing can be by a party in Persecution who have not ever had any oportunities or allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances to act in any case otherwise then each person of the party as a private person, and only in his private capacity: And they appeal to the Justice of those who profess to have the greatest Aversion of all others against the Religion of the <hi>Papists,</hi> whether they will admit it as a rule that the Villanies of some private persons, who profess themselves to be in fellowship or communion with any Church or people, calling themselves Christians, may in Justice and ought in reason to be charged as proceeding from the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, Doctrines, or Religion of that Church or people with which private persons profess to be in communion or fellowship? they cry out, God forbid any such rule should have credit in the World.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:206886:10"/>
            <p>On the other side, I am not ignorant, that the <hi>Papists</hi> who E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem the <hi>Protestants</hi> in general as their mortal enemies, by whom they apprehend themselves to have been deprived of what is most dear unto them, from the time that the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion first gained a preheminency in <hi>England,</hi> are as highly Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table towards the <hi>Protestants,</hi> as these are severe in their censures towards them. They look upon the <hi>Protestants</hi> as the <hi>Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> did upon the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> they charged upon them the guilt of all the Blood that hath been shed, of all the Persecutions which have hapned for matters of meer Religion, since the first Act of Parliament of that Nature, made by King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. unto this hour; insinuating, that what was so cruelly acted by Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Bishops, was occasioned by the Provocations given in the time of King <hi>Edw.</hi> the 6th and warranted (as far as ill Acts can be warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) first, by the <hi>Non-conformists</hi> retaliations towards the Church of <hi>England,</hi> when subdued by them upon the Death of King <hi>Charles</hi> the first, and then by the present Retaliation made to the <hi>Non-conformists</hi> by those of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> since the Restauration of our present Soveraign. In short, as the <hi>Protestants</hi> in general, to excuse and Justifie themselves, labour to cast Persecution for matters of meer Religion upon the <hi>Papists,</hi> as a principle of Popery; so the <hi>Papists</hi> are as Industrious to perswade the World that it is a principle of Protestancy. I might here by way of Apology and Extenuation refer the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,</hi> as they do the <hi>Protestants,</hi> to consider of Circumstances of times and things which occasioned their Severities against them, as the unruliness which might probably be amongst the people in the time of King <hi>Edw.</hi> the 6th to see their Religion altered as they conceived, by the <hi>Protector.</hi> And in Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time, besides the resentment which the <hi>Protestants</hi> had of the Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which were exercised against them in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> time, It is certain, the <hi>Papists</hi> did not look upon Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to have any Right to the Crown; she having been declared by the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial Sentence, and Judgment of Arch-Bishop <hi>Cranmer</hi> to be Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligitimate; and the Marriage between King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Bullen</hi> her Mother, being by the same Sentence declared ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely void <hi>ab Initio,</hi> and that Sentence confirmed by Act of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:206886:10"/> Parliament, 28. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. C. 7. So that the <hi>Papists</hi> took Q. <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> to be the Rightful Heir to the Crown, and Rightful Queen, and Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was constarined by great necessity to keep them under; but Apologies are not proper to be made on the behalf of those, who have the Authority towards those who are subjected.</p>
            <p>And as the <hi>Protestants</hi> in general, and the <hi>Papists,</hi> reproached each other, reciprocally charging upon each other that Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for matters of meer Religion was a principle of each others Religion; so did the <hi>Episcopal Protestants,</hi> and the <hi>Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists:</hi> The <hi>Episcopal</hi> party, who first persecuted the <hi>Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists</hi> under the general Name of <hi>Puritans,</hi> or <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> affirmed, that their first beginners in <hi>Scotland,</hi> from whence they derived themselves, did more then any Party upon Earth Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute others for matters of meer Religion, and had gained a Power by their Usurpation, Oppression and Persecution, being a sort of People who wanted the very essentials (as they said) of Religion, viz. a right Ordination, without which (as they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge) there could be no true Church, no true Ministry or true Sacraments: And that, therefore they ought by Penal Laws, timely made, to be prevented from making Disturbances in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> The <hi>Puritans</hi> to justifie themselves, denying Persecution for matters of meer Religion to be their Principle, or to be lawful, laboured to fix it upon the Church of <hi>England</hi> as their Principle, and as taken up by them from the <hi>Papists.</hi> And as to the particulars charged upon those of <hi>Scotland,</hi> they said, That whatsoever those of the Reformation had done in <hi>Scotland,</hi> was approved and abetted by Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the <hi>Protestants</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> without whose advice nothing in <hi>Scotland</hi> had been Transacted, and without whose assistance things had not been so Effected; they further said as to the point of Ordination, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> ought not in reason, to account <hi>Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal</hi> Ordination to be such an essential of Religion as they char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, for that if no Ordination could be valid but by Bishops, that then it would follow, that no Ordination could be valid but from true and rightful Bishops of the true Church of Christ; and then the Ordination of the Church of <hi>England</hi> would be as invalid as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:206886:11"/> the Ordination of those of <hi>Scotland;</hi> for the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> could make out no Succession of Bishops, but through the Popish Church, which bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> partie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (as well those of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Scotlan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) had con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emned and agreed to be a false Church, and no true Church of Christ, but an Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot and <hi>Anti-Christian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Episcopal Protestants</hi> and the <hi>Puritans</hi> charged and recriminated each other, the <hi>Episcopal</hi> party nevertheless making good their ground, so long as they had the Civil Power to support them; but when upon the Death of K. <hi>Charles</hi> the first, the <hi>Non-conformists</hi> gained the civil Power into their Hands, the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> party (like all parties opprest) being under Persecution together with the <hi>Papists</hi> for matters of meer Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>Did absolutely condemn all such persecutions as unlawful;</hi> and then the <hi>Non-conformists</hi> (who were at that time sub-divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and brancht out into several other parties) gave occasion to charge them with the Principle of Persecution for meer Religion, and put them to use the same Arguments to clear themselves, as the <hi>Episcopal</hi> Party and <hi>Papists</hi> had respectively before made use of, when the Government was in them, to prevail with the World, to believe that they abhorred the principle of Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for meer Religion; and that the Persecutions used by them, were not for any matters of meer Religion, nor in Truth Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, but purely acts of prudence, and doing right to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves by a just care to keep the <hi>Episcopal</hi> party and the <hi>Papists</hi> out of all possibility of persecuting them any more for the future. But none of them could find any reason of that Nature to excuse the Persecutions, which they used towards the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> they could not charge them with ever having persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any Party or Person: yet in Fact, both the <hi>Non-conformists</hi> and the <hi>Episcopal</hi> party did Persecute them in their turns; and therefore to prevent being charged for persecuting a quiet Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for matters of meer Religion: They pretended sometime that the <hi>Quakers</hi> were all Mad-men, and that they Imprisoned them only to keep them out of the way, and to preserve them in peace; and those who had gotten the Government, would upon that very Title claim the right of judging what persons were Mad, as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:206886:11"/> they did alwayes of judging what was Truth and what Error; At other times they pretended to punish the <hi>Quakers</hi> as Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and the Persecutors being the only Judges of what was Blasphemy under their Government, they might make what they plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed Blasphemy. When they gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w ashamed of this charge, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey then pretended that the <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kers</hi> were concealed <hi>Papists,</hi> and that every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> spoke or uttered any thing in their Meetings (whether Man or Woman) was a Jesuit dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guized, it was clear that the <hi>Quakers</hi> suffered highly, and it was as clear there could not with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny shew of Truth be any thing charged against them, but what was matter of meer Religion.</p>
            <p>Now upon the whole matter, what shall such a person judge of these matters, who esteem himself in danger of being judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God, if he shall make any rash Judgment? Shall we take for a sufficient solid proof, the charge of an exasperated Enemy against an Enemy who hath provoked him, and this in a matter of so great a concernment, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to render not a single Person but a whole Party unworthy to live? this were to judge against the Rules of common Justice and Righteousness, as well as to Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Charity; and this way of judging would render each Party (the <hi>Quakers</hi> only excepted) to be Guilty, and to give a just Title to each Party, where it hath the possession of Power and Government to put to Death all of the other parties: For though we in <hi>England</hi> should refuse to admit the charge of the <hi>Papists</hi> here to be a sufficient proof against the <hi>Protestants</hi> in so great a matter; yet let u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not deceive our selves so far, as to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose that in Popish Countries, the charge of <hi>Papists</hi> against <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> would not be taken to be at the least as valid, as the charge of <hi>Protestants</hi> will be taken to be against <hi>Papists</hi> here. Shall we go another way, and say, that in regard every Party takes it self to be the only go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and true <hi>Christian,</hi> and in regard we see every Party, when in Power, practising this thing, and persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the other (when in their power) for matters of meer Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that therefore every Party agrees in this? <hi>That it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for those who are the true</hi> Christians, <hi>to make and execute penal Laws against such as are erronious</hi> Christians, <hi>and to Inflict pains and penalties upon them for matters of meer Religion, that is, for Errors held by them as Doctrines of Religion:</hi> But neither will
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:206886:12"/> this be reasonable or convenient, for this will also give Title to those who have the actual Power, and are in the possession of each respective Government in the <hi>Christian</hi> World, to put to death, and destroy all within their respective Jurisdictions, whom they judge to be Erronious <hi>Christians:</hi> And this will be also to Entitle the civil Magistrate in every <hi>Christian</hi> Country, to the absolute and uncontroleable right of judging between Truth and Error, so as to have no appeal from his definitive Judgment, and to entail against common sence, an Infallibility in the civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate of every Country of determining in matters of Faith and Religion; <hi>I say against common sence, for</hi> Christianity <hi>teacheth us that there can be but one true Faith; and if this power of judging should be allowed to the civil Magistrate,</hi> there would be as many Faiths as there are Governments amongst <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians;</hi> that would be true Faith in one Country, and the denyal of it punishable with death; which in another Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try would be an Error and a false Faith, and the affirming of it punishable with death, it would also be to justifie not only what the <hi>Papists</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> but what both the <hi>Papists▪</hi> and <hi>Protestants</hi> in all other parts cast as a charge upon our Nation, that the only Rule of Faith in <hi>England,</hi> is the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> that nothing is true <hi>Christian</hi> Doctrine in <hi>England,</hi> nor any Translation or Sence, or Interpretation of Scripture, a true Translation or Sence, or Interpretation of Scripture in <hi>England,</hi> but what is judged so to be by the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, albeit in the Statute made 2, 3 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. C. 1. Entituled, <hi>An Act for the uniformity of Service and Administration of the Sacraments throughout the Realm,</hi> it was affirmed by the then Parliament, that the then Book of Common-prayer enjoyned by that Statute to be used was <hi>made by the aid of the Holy Ghost,</hi> yet that very Book was by that very Parliament altered and amended as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the Statute 5 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. C. 1. And it hath received several Reformations and Amendments since, and was in and by a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> days, judged to be Heretical.</p>
            <p>As to my own Judgment in this particular affair, it leads me to another way of reasoning and discoursing, I do, and I think I am bound in Charity to believe that every person and party who prosesseth Christiantity, do at least intend to be what they profess,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:206886:12"/> and that they do all in their hearts fully give consent unto all those common Doctrines of Christianity, which, as standing Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of that pure Religion, were never questioned or denyed by any sort of Christians, such as are those which I have before observed, of <hi>doing unto others, as we would have others do unto us,</hi> and of <hi>not doing evil, that good may come of it,</hi> and those others of <hi>loving our Neighbours as our selves, yea, and of loving our very Enemies, and doing good to them who hate us and use us dispightfully;</hi> all which, when soberly considered, without passion or human interests are as expresly against all Persecutions for matters of meer Religion, and do not only tie up <hi>Protestants</hi> from destroying of <hi>Protestants</hi> but also even from Persecuting of any sort for any matters of meer Religion, as those commands, <hi>Thou shalt do no Murther, thou shalt not Steal, thou shalt not commit Adultery,</hi> are against and tye up all Christians from shed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood Unlawfully, and Malitiously, and against Rapine and Uncleanness. And do also in their hearts believe that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever counsel or work is of man, will fall of it self; and that what is of God will stand Maugre all the Persecutions and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions of man, and that there is none of them do intend to fight against God or would willingly be found so doing. All this being taken by me in my own thoughts, to be most certainly true, when ever I come to enquire, How then can these things be? How can all these parties (among which there are great numbers of good, sober, Judicious and Sincere persons) offend against these common Principles of the common faith of all Christians, by making and executing Penal Laws for matters of meer Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>Immediately adjoyn</hi> to this another Question, which is, And how can so many persons, professing to be Christians, take revenge by Blood, usurp the goods of their Neighbours, and commit the Sin of Uncleanness; yet all these were done by that great and good King, and Prophet, who was <hi>a man after Gods own Heart.</hi> That which to me answers this latter Question, seems clearly to solve the former, that the <hi>Beast</hi> gets Dominion over the <hi>Man,</hi> the passions commit a force upon reason; and Human frailty, being too weak, brings the best of men sometimes (though but for a time) and careless men oftentimes to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:206886:13"/> their faith by their practice, until by afflictions they gain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, and come to repentance for the saving of their Souls. This to me seems so evident a Truth, that until, something more evident shall convince me of my being mistaken in this, I should think it as great a sin against Charity, for me to charge it as a Principle of the Religion of any party (professing to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians) <hi>That Persecution for meer Religion is Lawfully,</hi> because I see it practised by those who have power amongst that party, as to charge the same party, to hold it as a Principle of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that Murther, Theft and Adultery are Lawful, because great numbers of that party, are two often guilty of the practice of those sins.</p>
            <p>If this way of considering things be not found unreasonable, but upon due reflection, shall appear to be conformable to the true Principles of Christianity, and the holy Rules and Doctrines of Christ, I hope those who are Publick persons will forgive me when I wish they would lay it to their hearts, and think well whether it would not be of use to preserve this poor Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from the further guilt of those additional Injustices, and Cruelties which the contrary way of rash Judging must involve and daily do involve us in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is not more calm Judgment to say,</hi> that the Disordinate passions of K. <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth hurried him into those cruelties which he committed, then to impute them to the Principles of any Religion which he professed? Is it not more becoming us to say that an over-zealous passion of fears which our first Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers had in the time of K. <hi>Edw.</hi> the sixth made them appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that they could not put Popery out of its possession other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise then by force, and consequently led them unwarily into practices, which were contrary to their <hi>true faith,</hi> then to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the charge laid on them by the then Persecuted <hi>Papists, that Persecution for meer Religion, was the first</hi> Protestant Principle <hi>upon which</hi> Protestancy <hi>laid its first Foundation in</hi> England, were it not more ingenious to attribute the Cruelties, which were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s time to the passion of Fear in that Queen, and of Fear and Covetousness in her Bishops, that nothing could secure her against New Rebellions from the <hi>Protestants,</hi> nor
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:206886:13"/> fix the Bishops in their re-gained Possessions, but Examples of the utmost rigour, Then to labour to fix those Barbarous Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties as a Principle upon the Religion of that Queen. Is it not more Charitable to assign all the harsh Laws made and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in the times of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> and in the several succeeding times since by the Government avowedly <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant,</hi> to the Fear, Ambition, Revenge, or other frail Passions, covered generally under the specious Titles of <hi>Reason of State,</hi> then to give the World a just Ground to charge those Cruelties upon a Principle of <hi>Protestancy.</hi> This we must do, or (which is as much to our Dishonour) we must give a just Ground to the most civillized Nations of the World, to charge those past Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barities, exercised so long in <hi>England,</hi> upon the people of our Nation, to the Cruelties of our English Natures: For what other thing can forraign Nations impute it unto, when they shall observe the same persecution continued for near one hundred and forty years, under all the various Forms of Religion which we have had, each party renouncing the Cruelties to proceed from any Principle of the Religion owned by that party, yet exercising in practice what they profess to renounce to be their Faith.</p>
            <p>But my Charity doth not rest here, it compels me to make yet one step further; and since it is not to the Dishonour of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I hope none will be displeased with it: As I am verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded, that all those penal Laws, which have been made in this our Nation for the inflicting of Pains and Penalties for matters of meer Religion, have not had their Original from any Principle of any of those Religions which have been professed by any of those Powers or Governments by which they were made, but ought to be imputed to the Passions of those who made and caused them to be put in execution: And that a false Reason of State gave those Passions leave to work even against the Religion which every Party persecuting, professed; so do I most confidently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the true Principles of the common <hi>Christianity,</hi> which every Party owned, and true Reason of State grounded upon those true and commonly owned Principles, restrained all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the respective partie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by whom those Laws were made, from all intentions of having all or any of those Laws rigidly executed; so that those who had from time to time, and who still have the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:206886:14"/> executive and interpretative Power of those Laws vested in them, have alwayes understood, and do still continue to understand those Laws not to have been intended by the Legislative Power to be <hi>strictly</hi> and <hi>rigidly</hi> or <hi>constantly executed;</hi> my Reason is, that had this been otherwise, All of All parties, except One, who at some time had been in power, must have been ere this totally butchered or destroyed, and our poor Country so far depopulated as to have become a prey to some of our potent Neighbours.</p>
            <p>I know some there are who have imputed the remiss execution of these unkind Laws to the generous good nature which is found in the generality of our Nation, which abhors cruelty, and hath alwayes a compassion for those who are under Persecution; and which well appears to any who reflect upon the tenderness of our Courts of Justice, and of the generality both of our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, and our Juries in all the Countries of <hi>England,</hi> and how they have comported themselves under the several circom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of past times when they have been called upon and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked, yea threatned, and endeavoured to have been forced into a Spirit of Persecuting.</p>
            <p>Others there are who have taken the great unwillingness in all sorts of persons to be active in the execution of these Laws to proceed from the innate zeal that is in every <hi>English</hi> man to preserve the liberties and properties of their fellow Subjects, as well as their own; and that they have observed, that liberty and property were never any way so much entrencht upon violated and destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as by these cruel Laws of Persecution for meer Religion; so that every man considering when he sees his Neighbour (though differing in Judgment from himself) Persecuted and destroyed for what ought to be called, rather his mistake then his fault (for no man can believe against this Judgment, or take an Oath against his Conscience without sin) that though this be his Neighbours turn this year, it may be his own turn the next year; &amp; no mans Life, Liberty or Property can be secure in case of such Laws executed, but only such men who have a Conscience fitted for all changes of Government, and for every Religion that is uppermost, and who for that reason are as unfit to be trusted by their Neighbours as by the Government.</p>
            <p>But though I take it to be very true that this natural incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:206886:14"/> to mercy and pity, and this real zeal which all men have for the preserving of liberty, and property may have been great helps to keep off or mitigate the severe Execution of these Laws of Persecution for meer Religion; yet when I well consider the great Power, and influence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which the supreme Authority alwayes hath upon the Subjects; and particularly upon all the Magistrates in general, who are alwayes persons nominated and appointed by the Suprem Authority; and must be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therefore supposed to be such as in whom the Supreme Authority alwayes confides, as to the due Execution of what the Supreme Authority intends to have Executed; I think it will Naturally follow, that a forbearance of the rigid Execution of these Laws, ought to be chiefly imputed to the Religion and true <hi>Christian</hi> policy of the Supream Authority; and we ought to believe, that though a false Reason of State did sometimes permit human frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to make such Laws as were contradictory to the true Laws and Principles of that very Religion which those persons pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed, by whom those Laws were made; yet true Religion, and true reason of state alwayes kept those persons from intending to have those Laws rigidly and severely Executed: I will confirm this by one single Instance of the highest Nature, and that not in the best of times. The last Popish Priest that was put to death in <hi>England</hi> for being a Priest of the <hi>Romish</hi> Church, was put to death in the time of <hi>Cromwell;</hi> I suppose, we are not to doubt of the passionate heat which inflamed those who were then in Authority against the <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Popery;</hi> they looked on the <hi>Papists</hi> as mortal Enemies to their Government, and as fast Friends, and devoted Servants to the Crown and Royal Family: Notwithstanding which, when the said Priest came upon his Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al at the Sessions-house in the <hi>Old Baily</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and upon his Arraignment, pleaded that he was not Guilty of Treason, but acknowledged himself to be a Priest of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; It clearly appeared that those who were his Judges, did their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most to preserve his Life, and to prevent the Execution against him of those Laws upon which he stood Indicted: For they did for many hours suspend the recording of his Confession, making it their endeavour to prevail with him to plead <hi>not Guilty</hi> to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:206886:15"/> Indictment; they pressed him to this in the publick Court, assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he would so plead, his Life should be safe; and that they had no evidence which could prove him to be a Priest. And when the Old Man (Aged about seventy two Years) would not be drawn to deny himself to be a Priest; (taking it to be a dying of his Religion) so that the Court was compelled to give Judgment against him; The Magistrate who gave t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Sentence, was so drowned in Tears upon that sad occasion, that it was long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could pronounce the Sentance, which the Law compelled him (as he professed) to give. Now I ask, can it be presumed that in those severe times against <hi>Popery,</hi> those who then sate upon the Seat of Justice, would, or durst have proceeded t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us in a publick Court, and made it their business so openly, so avowed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have saved the Life of a Priest of that party, if they had not well considered that the makers of those Laws, and even <hi>Cromwell,</hi> who had then taken upon him the Government of these Nations, did not in Truth intend a rigid and severe Execution of those Laws, which were for Inflicting Pains and Penalties for matters of meer Religion?</p>
            <p>But I think, I need give no further Instances for the proof of this my Opinion: whosoever shall reflect upon the present genius of our whole Nation, and consider in what detestation all men have the Execution of persecuting Laws for matters of meer Religion; How publickly Informers are abhorred and discoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, when they labour to persecute any upon any such Law, will easily see that the whole Nation in general is Convinced, that those Laws were never any of them made, with intention to have them rigidly Executed. I have been told, (and it seems to be grounded upon Reason) that it is a principle of our Laws, <hi>That even an Act of Parliament, which is against the Law of God, or against Reason, is void in it self;</hi> if this be true (as me thinks it ought to be) I think we are very near the time, wherein all our present Laws of this Nature, by which any are subject to be in any measure persecuted for matters of meer Religion, will be repealed by the general Voice of the whole Nation, and that when the particular Persons, of which the great Body of this Nation is composed, shall have considered something more
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:206886:15"/> deliberately then their Passions have yet permitted all to do, that every Law of this nature is against the Liberty and Property of the Subjects of <hi>England;</hi> unjust and cruel, in punishing men for not proceeding against their Consciences; expresly against the very Principles and Rules of the Gospel of Christ, and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of that true Religion which every one of us pretends to own; destructive to the Trade and well being of our Nation, by oppressing and driving away the most industrous Working Hands of our Nation, and depopulating, and thereby impoverish our Country, which is capable of imploying ten times the number of people which we now have; contradictory to the Rule of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, grounded upon common Reason, as well as Religion, which requires, <hi>That no man should do unto another, what he would not have done unto himself,</hi> and consequently void in it self by the Rule of the Laws of our own Country: There will not be found a Magistrate, nay, a common Subject in <hi>England,</hi> who will not as positively renounce the putting in execution, or being accessary to the executing of any Law of this Nature, as he will renounce the becoming guilty of those detestable Sins of Murder or Theft. But until men are a little further convinced of these Truths, you (Sr.) ought not to be angry with, but rather pity those Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates from whose Hands you have lately suffered for a Matter meerly of Religion: Peradventure they did not fully consider, that the Matter with which you were charged, was a Matter of meer Religion, but took the Meeting in an Assembly meerly for the Worship of God, <hi>to be an Ʋnlawful Assembly,</hi> because prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a present Law, as the poor Magistrates in the Apostles times took their Meetings in their Assemblies meerly for the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God, to be Unlawful Assemblies, &amp; Breaches of the Peace, because they were prohibited by their Laws: Or perhaps their Fear that they should themselves be subject to a Forfeiture, in case they should have denyed their Warrant to the Informer, made them fall under that Human Frailty for the securing of themselves. However it was, I suppose you have no just Ground to believe the thing to be any Effect of Malice against you or your Friends; and if it be not, then the same Magistrates, now their Fear is over,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:206886:16"/> may yet be instrumental to do you and themselves Right. It is Odds but upon a strict Reflection upon what the Informer hath sworn, the Devil may have prevailed with him to swear some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which may be proved untrue; for Informers are not squeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish in swearing for their own profit, as it daily appears in <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster-Hall</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> and one point of Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>jury proved will invalidate all his Testimony, and reverse all that is done: At which I am very confident no man (besides the Informer) will be displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. And this is in plain Truth the great Reason why your Friends here desire to know all the Circumstances of your Case; the certifying of which may be an Advantage to your self and your Friends there, and will be particularly very Welcome unto</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sr.</salute>
               <signed>Your Old True Friend, <hi>A. N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:206886:16"/>
            <head>Postscript</head>
            <p>I Have here omitted many of those great Arguments, both which others have used, and which may yet be advanced from the Nature of this Subject, partly because there are so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Discourses</hi> extant, and partly because English Mankind begins to be satisfied in the Matter. Yet this give me leave to add in general, That Force upon Conscience, and corporal Penalties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Matters of Religion, have not only no President or Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from Christ or his Apostles, but are expresly <hi>against</hi> both their <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Examples.</hi> This Coertion is the old Disturber of States, the Destroyer of Property, the Depopulator of Kingdoms, the Enemy of Human Nature, of Kind Neighbourhood, and of Conscientious Religion. At best it either maketh men <hi>Religious by Rote,</hi> which is <hi>no Religion;</hi> or <hi>conformable for Fear and Interest,</hi> which is <hi>Ir-religion</hi> and base Hypocrisie. But besides all this, it corrupteth and distracteth the Nature of all <hi>Civil Government,</hi> by making the measure of Loyalty, not <hi>Love, Honour</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> to <hi>Caesar,</hi> but <hi>Conformity</hi> to the Clergy and Religion in Fashion; which destroyes the true Dependence and Obligation in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and subjects the Lives, Liberties and Estates of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the frequent Revolutions of Religion; which ought to stand fixed and sacred upon the common and undeniable Principles of Civil and Just Government. I hope I shall be excused for <hi>this Conception,</hi> since of all others, <hi>this renders to</hi> Caesar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caesars: and I would to God, all the <hi>Caesars</hi> of the World saw the Truth of this <hi>Notion:</hi> They would not then suffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be <hi>grown upon,</hi> not only by another Power then <hi>Caesars,</hi> but by a Power <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>Caesars,</hi> and which in the tendency of it leaves <hi>Caesar</hi> nothing but <hi>his Name.</hi> We might hope, he would not be less kind to his People, then <hi>Hens</hi> are to their <hi>Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens;</hi> not expose them to the <hi>Tempest,</hi> nor the cruel <hi>Tallons</hi> of the Birds of Prey; but cover, defend and comfort them under
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:206886:17"/> his Wing of Just Power and Favour, endeavour their Encrease, encourage their Industry, and thereby enrich and replenish the Kingdom, not impoverish and depopulate them; For <hi>the Glory of a Prince is in the Multitude of his people,</hi> not Beggars, but <hi>men of Industry:</hi> But who dare be industrous now adayes, that would not have his Labours made the <hi>Forfeit</hi> of his <hi>sober Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</hi> UNHAPPY AGE! <hi>Come,</hi> 'tis time for Humane Nature to remember from whence she came, for Man and <hi>to love,</hi> for <hi>Caesar to be kind to all his people,</hi> to let his Rain fall upon all, his Sun-shine upon all, that he may justly render himself Master of the <hi>Affections</hi> of all; and not interest nor imbroyle his Government with the opinionary Differences o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Religion, which doth not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large, but <hi>narrow</hi> his Empire: and those that put him upon such measures, they do <hi>Ill Offices</hi> in the great Family of the Kingdom: They set the Father <hi>against the Son,</hi> and excite him to disinherit his Children, and those <hi>virtuous too,</hi> meerly for the sober exercise of a dissenting Conscience, about Matters relating to t'other World. This is <hi>practising Reprobation for Opinion, and sacrificing Nature and Morality to Modes of Religion:</hi> nay, this is to <hi>engross</hi> Caesar <hi>by a Party, and to monopolize him from the rest of his people;</hi> a Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the very Nature and end of Government. God grant us all more Wisdom, more Honesty and more Charity, and that we may yet live to see <hi>all industry encouraged, the Poor employed, the Kingdom in love with its own Growths, Virtue only rewarded, Vice only punisht, that</hi> Righteousness, Peace <hi>and</hi> Plenty <hi>may yet vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to dwell amongst us. So be it to</hi> Caesar <hi>and his people, while the Sun and Moon endares.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.
<pb facs="tcp:206886:17"/>
         </trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>